<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of Mr. Iustice Cook's passage by sea from Wexford to Kinsaile and of the great storm and eminent danger that he with others were in, with the wonderful appearance of the power &amp; goodness of God in their deliverance according as it was revealed to him in a dream : as also M. Deedate with other witnesses (in Genevah) opinion concerning dreams occasioned by a remarkeable profettick dream of a Protestant marques daughter in Poland / all faithfully communicated as received from his own hand in the year 1650.</title>
            <author>Cook, John, d. 1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95177</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2912</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30272</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11281662</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11281662</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151418</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95177)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151418)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1458:7 or 2258:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of Mr. Iustice Cook's passage by sea from Wexford to Kinsaile and of the great storm and eminent danger that he with others were in, with the wonderful appearance of the power &amp; goodness of God in their deliverance according as it was revealed to him in a dream : as also M. Deedate with other witnesses (in Genevah) opinion concerning dreams occasioned by a remarkeable profettick dream of a Protestant marques daughter in Poland / all faithfully communicated as received from his own hand in the year 1650.</title>
                  <author>Cook, John, d. 1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The 2d. edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by T.B. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652?</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title reads: A relation of Mr. John Cooks passage by sea from Wexford to Kinsale, being the great storm on January the 5th.</note>
                  <note>This item appears at reel 1458:7 as Wing C6023 (entry cancelled in Wing (2nd ed.)), and at reel 2258:26 as Wing (2nd ed.) T2912.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library and British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Providence and government of God.</term>
               <term>Visions.</term>
               <term>Irish Sea --  Storm, 1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151418:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A True RELATION Of Mr. <hi>Iuſtice Cook's</hi> paſſage by Sea from <hi>Wexford</hi> to <hi>Kinſaile,</hi> and of the great Storm, and eminent danger that he with others were in, with the wonderful appearance of the power &amp; goodneſs of God in their deliverance, according as it was revealed to him in A DREAM. As alſo M. <hi>Deedate</hi> with other witneſſes (in <hi>Genevah</hi>) opinion concerning Dreams occaſioned by a remarkeable profettick Dream of a Proteſtant Marques Daughter in <hi>Poland.</hi> All faithfully communicated as received from his own hand in the Year, 1650.</p>
            <q>They that go down to the Sea in ſhips: and do their buſineſs in great waters: Thoſe ſee the works of the Lord: and his wonders in the deep, <hi>etc.</hi>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 107.23.24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31, 32.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Acts 27.22, to 26.</hi>
               </bibl> And now I exhort you to be of good cheere: for there ſhall be no loſſe of any mans life among you: For there ſtood by me this night the Angel of God, whoſe I am, and whom I ſerve. Saying fear not <hi>Paul</hi> thou muſt be brought be four Caeſar, and lot, God hath given thee all them that ſaile with thee. Wherefore Sirs, be of good cheere: for I beleeve God, that it ſhall be even as it was told me.</q>
            <p>The 2d. Edition,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed and are to be Sold by <hi>T. B.</hi> at the three Bibles neer the <hi>Weſt</hi> end of <hi>Pauls Chrch-Yard.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151418:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151418:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:151418:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151418:3"/>
            <head>A Relation of Mr. <hi>John Cooks</hi> paſſage by Sea from Wexford to Kinſale, being in the great Storm on <hi>Jannuary</hi> the 5th.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>The Lord is then beſt praiſed, when we acknowledge him to be his own praiſe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> 
               <hi>Annuary</hi> the firſt 1649. We embarqued from <hi>Wexford</hi> in the <hi>Hector</hi> for <hi>Corke,</hi> ſayled two or three leagues beyond <hi>Greenor-bay,</hi> but were driven back, the wind turning upon us, upon the Saturday following the wind being fair we got within ſight of <hi>Dungarvan,</hi> that night proved very windy, and about four in the morning, on the Lords day, a very tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wind aroſe, and the ſtorm was the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt that ever any of the Sea-men knew (as they ſaid) the wind was at South-eaſt very thick, we hoped to fetch <hi>Corke,</hi> being within a mile of the ſhore, but could not poſſibly make land: in that diſtreſs we put to ſea, hoping by that way to ſave life, the wind continued all that Sabbath day at South-eaſt, South-eaſt and by South, and South South-eaſt, which if the wind had held at ſouth-eaſt as it was in the morning, we could not have doubled the point about the land but had been eaſt upon the rocks: we bore two courſes to keep off from the ſhore all the day, and being as we ſuppoſed about the pitch of the Cape Cleere, at nine on Sabbath day night we ſhipt a great Sea which ſplit and carryed away our foreſaile, and ſo were forced to bring to a fore-top fail to keep from the ſhore, and to here that fore tope-ſaile till two in the night, in which time we were formed to cut our Anchor from the bough to ſave the ſhip from foundring, we having at that time five foot water in the hold. The Monday morning we were ten leagues to leeward of the Cape Cleere, and the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151418:4"/>wind was up at South-weſt, then we made all the ſayl poſſible to fetch ſome harbour, and it pleaſed God, we made the Cape, hoping to fetch <hi>Baltamore,</hi> but the wind coming up at South-eaſt and by eaſt, we were forced to Sea again all the night, the wind continuing at South-eaſt, South-eaſt and by South, and South-South-eaſt.</p>
            <p>Tueſday we made the Miſne head, and could fetch no harbour the wind being ſtill at South-eaſt. Wedneſday the wind came up at Weſt, and we made for ſhore again, and came up as high as <hi>Gally-head</hi> hoping to fetch <hi>Kinſale;</hi> about three in the after-noone the wind came up at Eaſt South-eaſt, and then we hoped to recover <hi>Caſtlehaven</hi> before night, and made for it, and in our running in, the Wind veared at South-eaſt and blew very freſh, and we ſtill hoping to gain the harbour, ranin, knowing no other way to ſave life, the Wind being ſo contrary, it grew extraordinary thick, rained and blew much, we fired three or four pieces of Ordnance (for lights) and ſaw one light from the Caſtle, as we ſuppoſed, and two other lights to the Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, which put us to an amazement, not knowing whether they were friends or enemies, and could not poſſibly ſee the going into the Harbour, but were in the very breach of the ſhore, the ſight where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of cauſed a great ſcrik in the Ship, and thereupon brought our Ship to, hoping thereby to have come to an Anchor, which if we had done, we had been paſt all hopes of life, the Rock being ſo neer would have cut our Anchor, but God being moſt merciful in that nick of time, the Sea-men deſpairing of life, the Wind at an inſtant came up at Eaſt, which carryed us into the Sea, and yet ſo great was the danger, that if the Wind did not turn again to the Weſt in leſs than half an hour, we were dead men, by reaſon of the Rocks called the <hi>Staggs,</hi> ſo we came in a little time within ſight of the Rocks, the Wind driving us ſtrongly upon them, and then ſeeing the Rocks within a Ships length of us, we put our Ship to ſtay, which ſhe would not, the Sea being ſo extremely grown, the Sea-men being at their wits end, wiſhing us to prepare for death: the Lord again at that very inſtent cauſed the wind to come up at South-weſt, which carryed us out into the Sea cleer from the Rocks, where we had the Wind favourable that night, and bleſſed be God on Thurſday we came into <hi>Kinſale,</hi> it being the firſt Harbour that the Lord was pleaſed to give us, but that which is moſt admirable is this, that ſo ſoon as the Ship was come into <hi>Kinſale</hi> Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, ſhe leaked ſo very much, that the Sea-men came the next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and told us, that they were almoſt drowned that night, and could
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151418:4"/>ſcarce keep the ſhip alive in the Harbour, and were forced the next tide to bring her to the Key, and at the Ebb to repair her, and had much ado to keep her from ſinking. This being the method of Gods dealing with us in our paſſage.</p>
            <p>Now concerning the work of God upon my ſpirit during the ſtorm, thus it was. Towards the evening of the Sabbath day <hi>Jannuary</hi> the 5. my heart was exceeding ſad and ſorrowfull even unto death a dark night approaching, and the ſhip taking in much water, my ſpirit fainted and my heart ſunk within me, the ſorrows of death caught hould of me, much grieved I was for my poor dear heart who did not expreſs half ſo much fear as my ſelf, many ſweet expreſſions ſhe uſed in prayers, wiſhing me to call earneſtly upon God: many words I could not uſe, but my heart was praying; it almoſt broke my heart to think what my wives friends would ſay in <hi>England,</hi> that I ſhould bring her into <hi>Ireland</hi> to drown her (though I bleſs God ſhe never repined at it) troubled I was likewiſe for my poor ſervants that came in love along with us; it almoſt ſplit my heart to think what the Malignants would ſay in <hi>England</hi> when they hear that we were drowned (how they would abuſe that paſſage of <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 28.4.) That though vengeance hath not overtaken me at Land, yet I was met withal at Sea; much troubled I was at the manner of the death, ſuch extraordinary violent deaths importing the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſome heavy Judgement, as if the Lord hath been diſpleaſed with us, and had not ſent us, and <hi>Jonahs</hi> ſtorm was much in my thoughts (I having ſpoken ſome words of Exhortation to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany out of that Scripture before the ſtorm began) for God ſent that great ſtorm, <hi>Jonah.</hi> 1.4. becauſe <hi>Jonah</hi> went contrary to his Commands, where I obſerved, That when a Chriſtian is in Gods way, upon Gods errand ſent to Sea, uſually God makes the Winde and the Seas fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable to him; upon ſuch conſiderations, and many obiections made by fleſh and blood, I had very much trouble with my unbelieving heart, and could not bring my mind to be willing to die, earneſt I had been in ſecret prayer at the Throne of Grace before, for 16. or 18. hours to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, pleading with the Lord, that if it were poſſible this cup of his indignation might paſe over us, that in Judgments he would remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Mercy, however that we might cheerfully ſubmit to his ſweet pleaſure; the materials of my long ſuggeſted prayers were meditations and applications of ſeveral Scriptures which mention Gods power,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151418:5"/>wiſdome and love in the Seas. God having put it into my minde not long before to note moſt of the chief places is Scripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Seas, as proper and uſefull for a Sea-voyage. I preſt my dear Chriſt not to drown us, for ſaid I, we fight for thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Office, throw the <hi>Agyptians</hi> and all thy emplacable enemies into the midſt of the Sea, but let us be preſerved that we may praiſe thy Name, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.27, 30. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.1. Lord this is a calamity too heavy for thy poor creatures to beare. <hi>Job</hi> 6.3 were it not that thou haſt caſt our ſins into the depths of the Seas: <hi>Micah</hi> 7.19. Lord ſuffer not the deeps to ſwallow us up: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.15. Let not all thy waves and billowes paſs over us. We have ſeen thy wonders in the deep: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.23. And if thou ſave us we ſhall declare them to the children of men; but if thou make our graves in the Sea, the dead cannot praiſe thee: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.17. thou Lord which leadeſt thy Servants through the deep, prepare dry Land for us: Lord, why ſhould not the Seas be as favourable to thy ſervants as the dry Land? Thou layeſt up the depth in ſtore-houſes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.7. Thou Lord canſt ſtill the noyſe of the waves, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65, 7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.22. was a comfortable place to me, that the Lord promiſed to bring again his people from the depth of the Sea. Sweet Chriſt do thy Office and be a Savour to thy people both for Souls and Bodies, thou layeſt the beames of thy Chambers in the waters 10.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3. and ruleſt the raging of the Seas. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.9. Now Lord the floods have lifted up their voyce and their waves: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 93.2. but thou art mightyer than the mighty waves of the Sea. The fiſhes of the Sea ſhall ſhrink at thy preſence: but why art thou ſo angry with thy ſervants who art ſent in thy ſervice? Lord caſt the great Dragon into the Bottomleſs Pit, that old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent called the Devil and Sathan. <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.9. but let thy people live to praiſe thee; thou Lord canſt ſay to the Sea, Be dry: <hi>Eſa.</hi> 44.27. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 50.2, and canſt eaſily bring us ſafe to land Lord haſt not thou made the depths of the Sea a way for thy ranſomed ones to paſs over? <hi>Eſa.</hi> 51.10. Why muſt then thy ſervants be drowned as if they were in this Malefactors? <hi>Ionah</hi> ran away from thee and would not obey thee, being unwilling to be the mouth and proclaimer of thy Iuſtice upon <hi>Nineveh</hi> the head of the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Empire; and thou ſenteſt out a great winde, and there was a mighty tempeſt in the Sea, <hi>Ionah.</hi> 4. which was no ordinary wind, but ſent as a puniſhment for his diſobedience, yet becauſe he was thy ſervant, and was not ſelviſh,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151418:5"/>nor diſpleaſed in thy ſhewing mercy for fear of his being thought a falſe Prophet, but out of zeal for thy glory which he thought was wronged and obſcured by that change, and out of his ardent affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to thy people that their enemies ſhould live; and though he ſaid, he did well to be angry, even unto death, they being not words of expreſſe rebellion, but of a paſſionate Spirit blinded with anger, therefore when he prayed unto thee out of the belly of Hell, he was mightily preſerved. Now Lord, thou which waſt a God ſo gracious and merciful ſlow to anger, &amp; of great kindneſs towards the Heathens in <hi>Niveveh</hi> ſhall not we find thy mercy? if thou haſt any further work for us to do in our generation, we ſhall. Lord, it is the wicked that is like the troubled Sea, whoſe water caſts up mire and dirt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.20 Thy Juſtice was very wonderful and glorious at <hi>Wexford,</hi> in drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe Pirates and wicked men in the Sea, that had done ſo much miſchief to thy people in that Element, and what will thy enemies ſay when the carkaſſes of thy people are given to be food for the Fiſhes? Lord command this great wind into thy treaſure, and bring forth winds ſerviceable for us that we may have an auſpicious gale, and an expeditious fail into ſome Harbour where it ſhall pleaſe thy Majeſty, for thy poor creatures are at their wits end, and death appears in their faces; thou only canſt ſhut up the Sea with doors, <hi>Job.</hi> 38.8. Thou makeſt the deep to boyle like a pot, and makeſt the Sea like a pot of oyntment, as if the Sea was hoary by the long white frothy path, <hi>Job.</hi> 41.31, 32. Sweet Chriſt, thou haſt dominion from Sea to Sea, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.8. and thou haſt given to the Sea a decree, that the waters paſs not thy commands, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.29. Therefore though the Sea Roar and threaten to ſwallow us up, yet unleſs thou giveſt it a commiſſion to devour us, it cannot hurt us: ſweet Chriſt, the Sea is unto thee as the dry land, the winds and Seas will obey thee, dear Redeemer wilt not thou ſpeak one word to ſave the lives of thy own members? <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.26, 27. <hi>and</hi> 14.27. <hi>Mark</hi> 4.29. Peace, Be ſtill, will make a great calm. Lord aſſure ſome of thy poor Servants that all ſhall be well, as thou didſt to bleſſed <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 27.23. Give ſome viſion and manifeſtation of thy love, for it was for thy ſake that we committed our ſelves to the Sea, let ſome of thy Servants in the Ship be aſſured from Heaven that we ſhall be ſafe, however Lord let thy will be our wills: with other Scriptures, not now perfectly remembred. Now after long Prayers and medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151418:6"/>it pleaſed God about ſix on the Sabbath day night, that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt began to quiet my Spirit in himſelf, and I was well perſwaded to die, and began to be raviſht with the Conſideration of the joyes of Heaven, how quickly I and my poor heart ſhould be in our Maſters joyes, that expreſſion of entring into my Maſters joy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected me much, that the joy was too big to enter into me, I muſt be ſwallowed up in it, and that my Maſters joy could be no ſmall joy; thereupon I ſpake comfortably to my wife, deſiring her to cheer up, for that we ſhould ſuddainly be in Heaven, if the Lord was pleaſed thus to take us to himſelf, who reſigned her Soul to God, and we took our leaves ſolemnly of each other, with our eyes full of teares, which I felt running down her cheeks when I kiſt them, ſaying that all tears ſhall ſuddenly be wiped from our eyes in Heaven, and with a great fervour of Spirit I thought ſeveral times to this purpoſe, Sweet Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus I come to thee, we come not only in this Sea of waters, but Lord we come to thee in a Sea of blood if it ſhall pleaſe thee to call us, the ſtorm ſtill increaſed, and I grew exceeding heavy and ſleepy, but rouſed my ſelf up, and checked my heart, that I ſhould <hi>Jonah</hi> like offer to ſleep in ſuch a ſtorm: what, be drowned in my ſleep! my wife often beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged at me not to ſleep, but I could not poſſibly forbear ſleep, if it had been to have ſaved all our lives; ſo it pleaſed God, that ſitting as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right as I could, I fell into as faſt a ſleep as ever I was in all my life.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:151418:6"/>
               <head>And in my ſleep I dreamed.</head>
               <p>THat I was in an upper chamber with my ſweet Redeemer Chriſt Jeſus, and that there were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Suiters attended to ſpeak with him, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech him to ſave their Ships and Barks, that they might not periſh by the ſtorm. I thought it was a large room, wherein there was a long table with an ordinary Carpet, and two candles ſtanding upon it, two trenchers of To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco, and Pipes, and one Man walking up and down by the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, of a middle ſtature, about thirty years of age, the hairs of his Head long and white as flax, but curling at the end, but the hair of his upper lip brown, in ſad colour'd cloathes, and a cloth broad brim'd hat; I asked him who he was, who ſaid, he waited upon Jeſus Chriſt; I asked him where Jeſus Chriſt was, he pointed to a Curtain, ſaying, there he is; I beheld and ſaw a glorious ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but no perſon, and methought Jeſus Chriſt ſpake to me, and asked me what I would have, I ſaid the lives of all in the Ship; ſaid he, in what ſhip? ſaid I in the <hi>Hector.</hi> It is a bad name ſaid he, for ſuch as profeſs me. <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux</hi> is for <hi>Heathens.</hi> I pray'd him that we might not dye in this manner; ſayes he to me, are not you ſafe? but good Lord ſaid I, I muſt return, and I beg life for all in the Ship; who are they ſaid he? I anſwered, that there was my dear Wife and three ſervants, Lieutenant Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Saunders,</hi> Major <hi>Bee,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hews,</hi> honeſt <hi>Abraham,</hi> and other paſſengers thy ſervants, (ſaid Jeſus Chriſt at my naming Lieu. Col. <hi>Saunders</hi> and ſome others, its ſo much the better that they are there) the Captain and the Sea-men are ſerviceable to thy Cauſe, and they take wonderful pains to ſave their own lives and ours, but unleſs thou ſpeak the word, the Sea will ſwallow us up. Then methought Jeſus Chriſt askt me why I was not willing to dye? I told him, that by this death I could not glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him, thinking upon that Scripture, <hi>Joh.</hi> 21.19. and methought I was ſomething impatient that the Lord ſhould ſurprize us, get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting us into a ſhip at his call for his ſervice, and then to drown us, as if we were Parricides or hainous Malefactors, which by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151418:7"/>Law were drowned: at that methought Jeſus Chriſt withdrew, as if he was diſpleaſed; ſaid I, Lord, if thou drowneſt thoſe that love thee, what wilt thou do to thine enemies? but could get no anſwer, whereupon I was ſenſible of my impatience, and thought that I fell down flat down on the ground, and cryed for mercy, ſaying, Lord, we kiſs thy Rod, and turn our naked backs; ſtrike as much as thou pleaſeſt. Lord, I plead nothing but thy free grace; it may be many of us have offended in exceſſive drinking, and now thou art puniſhing us in our own Element; however our ſins are more then the ſands of the Sea-ſhore, but let pitty move thee to ſave us; thou ſweet Redeemer which haſt been at Sea in ſtorms, that art a merciful High Prieſt, like unto us in all things but ſin, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.17. and 4.15. take pitty upon thine own fleſh and blood; what Father but would ſave his Child from drowning if he could? haſt thou no work for any of us to do? I thought the anſwer was, but little to be done by ſome of us; (my Wife tells me, that but a little before I ſlept, I ſaid, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly God had ſomething for me, and others to do for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and therefore we ſhould not dye at this time, which I did not remember;) ſweet Chriſt hear us as thou didſt thy Diſciples, ſave us quickly or elſe we periſh; and being earneſt in prayer, in my dream methought that the man in the room came to me, and told me that this was no natural ſtorm of Gods ſending, but an extraordinary tempeſt raiſed by Satan (by Gods permiſſion) to deſtroy thoſe which were coming to fight againſt his ſervants, and bad me uſe that argument to his Maſter. Thereupon I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly craved leave to ſpeak, and ſaid, Sweet Saviour, if this ſtorm and tempeſt be raiſed by Satan the Prince of the air, as in <hi>Lapland,</hi> and many other places where winds are ſold, he works in the children of diſobedience, and hath nothing to do with thy poor ſervants; for though thou mayſt juſtly for our ſins give Satan power over us, as thou didſt over thy dear ſervant <hi>Job,</hi> yet where thou giveſt a particular faith to be free from Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans ſtorms and witchcrafts, thou art pleaſed to grant that which is believed, And in great love it pleaſed Jeſus Chriſt to give a gratious anſwer to my ſpirit, and ſaid, Be not afraid, your lives ſhall be ſaved; inſtantly I replyed, Lord, let it be for all the Perſons in the ſhip; he ſaid, be it ſo; then I preſſed for the goods in the ſhip; Lord ſaid I, there are my L. G. goods, &amp; M. G. goods, Let them be ſafe; but they are not there, ſaid Jeſus Chriſt; no Lord ſaid I, they are fighting thy battels; Jeſus Chriſt anſwered, the goods ſhall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151418:7"/>all be ſafe, and the ſhip likewiſe, and nothing miſcarry; then I gave humble thanks, and departed; and as I was going out, I thought Jeſus Chriſt ſaid to me, it is granted for half fifty, go no more to Sea in Winter. I further dream'd that the Devil and his Imps were very earneſt with Jeſus Chriſt, to get leave to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Governour of <hi>Wexford,</hi> by the ſtorm; but the Lord ſaid, it ſhould not be; ſome there were that had Barks at <hi>Wex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> that attended to ſpeak with Jeſus Chriſt; I could not tell what they ſaid, they diſcourſed much about the Governour, and all that I heard Chriſt ſay, was, that winter was not yet come for them at <hi>Wexford;</hi> then I thought I met with Captain <hi>Haire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bottel,</hi> who had very great reſpect ſhewn to him, and I thought his prayers did us very much good, and he was very much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for his tenderneſs to the ſick Souldiers at <hi>Wexford.</hi> I thought there were other men from <hi>Wexford</hi> that came for ſafe paſſages, and one Officer was very earneſt for a ſhip that he was to come in, and I heard this expreſſion concerning him, we muſt take ſpecial care of his ſhip, for he was very tender and kind to the poor ſick ſouldiers, and much diſcourſe I heard about ſick ſouldiers. Jeſus Chriſt ſaid, if ſtorms will not do, I have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther afflictions to make them more tender-hearted and pitiful; methought the perſon that ſo walked in the room, ſpake much to this effect, that there would be many ſtorms by reaſon of much hardheartedneſs, to break and melt their ſpirits, ſince which (bleſſed be God) Captain <hi>Lucus</hi> is come ſafe in the wild <hi>Bear,</hi> one whom I obſerved in <hi>Wexford</hi> to be very liberal, tender-hearted, and compaſſionate to the poor Souldiers; whereupon I awaked: this dream laſted about two hours, all which time the ſtorm increaſed; my Wife told me that ſhe jogged me above twenty times to awaken me, and wondred that I ſhould ſleep, ſeeing we were all ſo near the point of death; ſaid I to her, peace my dear heart, be quiet, we ſhall all be ſafe: Jeſus Chriſt hath promiſed me our lives, be not afraid; and told her all my dream, whereat ſhe was much amazed, but could not believe any ſafety, and urged me to prayer, being her ſelf well reſolved to dye, cheerfully ſubmitting to Gods good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; but told me ſhe had a ſtrong impreſſion upon her ſpirit by way of queſtion, as if the Lord had ſpoken to her, that in caſe he ſhould be pleaſed to ſpare her life at this time, whether ſhe could be content to ſuffer for him? whereunto ſhe found her heart moſt ready and willing, by the Lords aſſiſtance, to lay
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151418:8"/>down her life for his glory; but my own heart was then gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thanks, and brim-full of comfort.</p>
               <p>I related my dream to Liutenant Col. <hi>Saunders,</hi> Major <hi>Bee, Ben.</hi> and the two Maids that were in the Cabbin. And ſent in for Captain <hi>Stoaks,</hi> the Maſter, the Gunner, <hi>Bennet,</hi> and Marſhal, and bid them be of good cheer, and ply their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for we ſhould be all ſafe, telling them what I had dream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; they admired at my confidence, and Captain <hi>Stoaks</hi> could not believe it, (ſaid he) I know God is very merciful and can do much; but the Ship hath five foot water in the hould, which the Pumpe could not reach, being choaked, and very ſubject to leaks, being twenty years old, and then it was about nine at night, the ſtorm increaſing, and they not knowing where about they were, I told them that I was aſſured of ſafety, as if I were on Shore, and one word more I had dreamed, which I told them of; ſaid I to Jeſus Chriſt, what if the Ship ſhould break aſunder? He anſwered me, you ſhall be as ſafe as if you were in <hi>Codds</hi> boat (a boat at <hi>Wexford</hi> that we went in towards the ſhip in the bay, and were driven back ſeveral times) or as if you were in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors houſe in <hi>Wexford;</hi> what impreſſion it had upon their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits I know not, but ſome that were in the great Cabbin told me that they did verily believe it, and that their hearts were much quieted by what I ſaid. The ſtorm increaſed, and a great noyſe was made in the ſhip, the water came in at the great Cab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin windows, the ſhip ready to overſet and to founder; many ſcreeks and cryes out, now we are gone, and yet my confidence and aſſurance increaſed, I bid them pray and be thankful, for they were as ſafe as if they were on ſhoar; ſtill my poor wife ſaid it could not be; I told her I was ſure of it; ſhe muſt lye ſtill and ſee the ſalvation of our God.</p>
               <p>I confeſs I much marvelled at the change that was wrought in my own ſpirit, from a trembling fearfulneſs to a rejoycing aſſurance; and conſidering it was but a dream, I thought I might preſume too much in an over-confidence, and was jealous over my own heart leſt I ſhould offend, begging the Lords extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary aſſiſtance ſutable to the preſent danger; but the more I checkt my heart of preſumption, the more did my faith mount upon the wing as if I had been upon dry ground, and had not ſo much fear as the thouſand part of the weight of a hair: the poor ſhip workt for her life, and the Sea-men took infinite pains, two parts being fallen ſick, &amp; the other 30. were continually at it, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151418:8"/>they were in a little hopes, ſometimes their ſouls ready to faint; about twelve at night, he that was at the Helm by my Cabbin ſaid all was broken, the water came in there; a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they cryed out, that the foreſail was ſplit and carried away, and the Anchors thrown over board to lighten the ſhip, yet all this while my ſpirit was the ſame, in a thankful admiration for ſo great a deliverance, and ſaid, all ſhall be as well as heart could wiſh; when they ſpoke of lightning the ſhip, my wife call'd to Capt. <hi>Stoaks,</hi> and bad him if he thought ſit to throw over ſome Trunks which we had in the ſhip, which I liked very well (as it was in <hi>Pauls</hi>-ſtorm) in regard of others that were in the ſhip, but for my own part, I ſaid I would not have any thing thrown over, for I knew all would be well, and (ſo bleſſed be the Lord of Seas) about four in the morning, the ſtorm abated, my heart was in a very thankful poſture, and that Wedneſday night after, when the Sea-men ſaid, we were in moſt danger, entring into <hi>Caſtle-Haven</hi> in the dark, that we muſt have the wind turn twice in half an hour to ſave us, firſt to carry us from the breach of the ſhore to the <hi>Staggs,</hi> and then to carry us off from them: when we were within a Cables length of the ſhore, and the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men divided, not knowing what to do, Captain <hi>Stoakes</hi> bad let fall an Anchor, or elſe we are all dead men, others ſaid, try to get off from ſhore, and there was a great ſcreek that all was gone, I was not one jot afraid, but told them they were fure to get ſafe to Land, and the ſhip to a Harbour, and the Lord ſhewed himſelf kind to poor ſinners.</p>
               <p>One thing, though it ſeem to be of ſmall importance, yet it runs much in my mind, and I muſt needs relate it; I thought that Jeſus Chriſt ſaid to me, that the goods ſhould be all ſafe, and nothing hurt or loſt by the ſtorm, but when we came to look for our things, we miſt a looking-glaſs and a Piſtol, the glaſs-caſe was all broke and ſhivered in many pieces by the rouling of the ſhip, being in one of the Boxes or Cabbin-cheſts in the great Cabbin among other things, but the Glaſs it ſelf was not ſo much as broken or crackt, and the caſe, though in eight or ten pieces, yet might eaſily be joyned and glued together, that it is not worſe by a farthing, which ſeems to me very admirable; I told Captain <hi>Stoakes</hi> of it, and deſired him, if poſſible, to help me to my Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol, he examined them about it, but it could not be heard of, till the very day the ſhip was going out of the Harbour, and then ſomebody that had it, could not be quiet till he brought it out,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151418:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>to let us ſee how weak our faith and confidence is in the Lord, and that he will perform with his poor ſervants to a Title of his promiſe.</p>
               <p>I know that uſually dreams follow mens natural inclination, or their daily converſation, as in <hi>Pharaohs Butler</hi> and <hi>Baker,</hi> they dreamed of wine and baskets of meat, matters about which they were ordinarily imployed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 40. and I having been in a continued meditation of Jeſus Chriſt his love, power, bowels of pity towards his members, it was moſt likely, that if I dreamed of any thing I ſhould dream of him, as many times upon the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both night I have dreamed that I was in the very ſame compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and at the ſame exerciſes as I was upon the day; and indeed the conſideration of Chriſts humanity, his being at Sea, and his experimental knowledg of our miſeries much ſupported me; how many prayers did we put up for a ſafe paſſage, which though they do not move the Lord by any eloquence, as an Orator moves his hearers, yet they move the Lord, as the cries of children make the bowels of their Parents yern towards them; and we muſt diſtinguiſh between ſhadows and ſubſtances; dreams are but the appearances of things which are not; natural dreams are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinful, deceitful and vain, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.8. the hungry thirſty man dreams, that he eats and drinks, but he awakes, and his ſoul is faint for food; or elſe they are repreſentations of things paſt, which were really done; or things to come, which falls out accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly; and the matter of the dream is principally to be regarded; ſome Chriſtians have had difficult places of Scripture expounded to them in their dreams, as they have told me.</p>
               <p>Therefore although dreams which are natural and ordinary, be of little or no account, yet extraordinary dreams many times prove true; as if one cry in his dream or be ſo faſt aſleep that he feels not pinching, when the Imagination is ſo extraordinarily powerful, and that the party dreaming is confidently perſwaded that it will come to paſs, it commonly proves accordingly, as that of <hi>Katharin de Medicis</hi> Queen of <hi>France,</hi> who dreamed that <hi>Hen.</hi> the ſecond ſhould be killed at the Tilt, and ſaid ſhe would venture her ſoul upon it. And ſo he was killed by a Scots man, <hi>Montgomery,</hi> as ſhe dreamed. <hi>Petrarch</hi> in <hi>Padova</hi> dreamed that a <hi>Scorpion</hi> ſtung him to death, that was in one of the Lyons that ſtand before a ſtatue which they fondly call <hi>Sancta Juſtina;</hi> the next morning he told his dream, went thither and put in his hand into the hole, and out came a Scorpion which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151418:9"/>poyſoned him, whereof he died: the great Souldier <hi>Fareſe</hi> the night before he dyed, dreamed that he was drowned, and that his Saint <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> could not carry him over the River, and the next day the Ferry-boat ſunk, and he was drowned.</p>
               <p>In 1629. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> a Proteſtant Marqueſſes Daughter in <hi>Poland</hi> dreamed that Jeſus Chriſt had told her comfortable things for the Proteſtants, as the good ſucceſs of the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> the death of the Emperors General <hi>Walſten;</hi> and that it might be the better believed, ſhe ſhould dye four days and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive again; one Miniſter <hi>Coturnius</hi> ſlighted it as a deluſion and vain fancie; ſhe told him that God was angry with him, and ſuch a day his only child ſhould die and himſelf preſently after, which both proved true; ſhe likewiſe fell into a Trance for eight and fourty hours, and then revived and foretold victories of the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> but that God would take him away, becauſe the people began to make a God of him, and thought him to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible. She dreamed that ſhe was married to Jeſus Chriſt, and that ſhe had a Crown of Glory promiſed her if ſhe could perſevere in the faith, and told her ſhe would be mockt and ſcoft at by many who would not believe but that ſuch viſions procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from imagination, melancholy humours, or weakneſs of brain, but bade her not be diſcouraged, ſhewing her a cup of blood, which he ſaid he would pour upon thoſe that perſecute his ſervants; and that ſhe prayed very earneſtly for the ſalvation of a deer friend of hers who was in arms againſt the Proteſtants, but that ſhe could not prevail for the ſalvation of any of her friends, but only for her ſelf, and that night the ſame party died; ſhe likewiſe in her dream ſaw two great perſons coming to be judged, one a Papiſt who had prayed much to his St. <hi>Francis,</hi> and deſired to be admitted into Heaven, but Jeſus Chriſt bad him go to Hell to Saint <hi>Francis,</hi> whither he was immediately dragged; and the other was a Proteſtant, who argued for his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation becauſe he fought againſt the Papiſts, and the Miniſters aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured him of Heaven: Jeſus Chriſt, ſaid he, will put out his candle in <hi>Germany,</hi> for it gives a falſe light, it ſhines without, but it is full of filth and ſelf-righteouſneſs within: ſhe likewiſe ſaw a man upon a Tree adored by many; and ſome Lyons came to the Tree and pluckt it down, and an Eagle was flying away, which the Lyons caught, and toar in pieces, and asking Jeſus Chriſt the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151418:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>meaning of that viſion, he told, that the man was that horrid beaſt the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> my capital enemy, not a Paſtor, but a Woolf, that ſays, behold I am ſet aloft, who dare come to touch me? the Lyons are the <hi>French, Engliſh, Swedes, Hollanders, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians</hi> and others that ſhall pluck down the proud beaſt, and pour out my wrath upon her, and her adherents, and that it ſhould begin about 1650. and be compleat by 1666. in her ſleep ſhe was heard to ſay; welcome Husband, and laughed heartily, and as ſhe awaked, ſhe ſaid, farewell dear Husband, and ſhe drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med many things more which fell out accordingly, being a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous child, naturally merry.</p>
               <p>In 1633. ſhe was married in <hi>Leſno</hi> in <hi>Poland,</hi> and moſt of the Miniſters in <hi>Germany</hi> have ſubſcribed to it, for they ſeriouſly conſulted about it, and ſent into <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Geneva,</hi> for aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and advice, and the reſult of the conference (which Mr. <hi>Deodate</hi> ſhewed me at <hi>Geneva</hi>) came to this; in <hi>Chriſtinaes</hi> dream, they did believe there was a Divine light: for firſt the young Lady was regenerate, and very zealous for the glory of God, ſo there was a good life in the perſon dreaming: Secondly, there was a full perſwaſion of heart that it was from God, and it would prove true: Thirdly, there was a certitude in the event, the party was not deceived, for it proved ſo, and it was likewiſe their judgements, that in a time of general perſecution, or ſome extraordinary eminent danger, God might and did many times ſpeak comfortable things to his people in dreams, as in the late <hi>Bohemian</hi> Wars, many <hi>Calviniſts</hi> were admoniſht in their dreams to go to places of ſecurity, which they attending, were ſafe from the enemy; as the Angel of the Lord appeared to <hi>Joſeph</hi> in a dream, and bad him flee with Jeſus Chriſt into <hi>Egypt, Mat.</hi> 2.13. and others that neglected ſuch dreams have afterwards re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented it.</p>
               <p>The Lord keep us all that were made partakers of ſo great a mercy, in an humble believing and thankful poſture, that we may ſpend the remainder of our new lives in the zeal of his ſervice, as thoſe that having their lives prolonged ſo extraordinarily are exceedingly obliged more then others to walk anſwerably to ſo great a mercy.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:151418:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
